[music]
Hello and welcome to the Junkyard Love.
>> Hey, everything's going to be all right.
>> It's all good. It's all good.
>> The Junkyard Love podcast. [music]
>> [music]
>> doing
the junkyard.
>> Two,
>> the title of your book is called Am I
Bipolar or Waking Up?
>> Hang on. Hang on. That's the first book.
>> The first book. Okay.
>> First book is am I bipolar or waking up?
Second book is bipolar awakenings. Okay.
And
>> so maybe we talk about both books. We
we've got some time. But yeah, the
second book, Bipolar Awakenings, will
have more implications for your
listeners.
>> Okay. Okay. So,
>> we can start with my bipolar waking up.
It's a good place to start.
>> I mean, I think it's probably all going
to weave into each other. Where I would
like to start is I would like to bring
in So, say somebody's tuning in and they
don't really know much about bipolar.
They don't they, you know, maybe we've
heard this term. Maybe they've heard of
someone who's been bipolar. Maybe the
most they know about bipolar is someone
who's like, well, I don't know, they
seem really happy and then suddenly
they're really ticked off. You know, the
the very uh uh thin uh explanation of
bipolar. So, can you tell me I guess
let's just start with what what is
bipolar for someone who's who's just
learning this.
>> Okay. So, bipolar disorder is like all
mental disorders in the big book of
mental disorders, the DSM, Diagnostical
Statistical Manual. It's a label given
to a set of symptoms. Okay? So, there's
no actual disease there that they can
find biologically. Okay? There's just a
set of symptoms. And what most people
think of as bipolar disorder, they would
label bipolar 2, which goes hypomomania
and depression. So, what's hypomomania?
Hypomomania tends to be symptoms like uh
not sleeping very well, non-stop or
incense in incessant speech, a lot of
business ideas, sometimes
hypersexuality,
sometimes some hyperaggressiveness,
and it just kind of feels like for the
outsider, it just feels like you're just
dealing with an extremely difficult
person. Okay? And that's the mania side
of things. spending lots of money, bad
investments, these kind of things, too.
Then it flips to the depression. Okay?
So, you've got this high, lots of
energy, spending lots of money, do all
these activities, driving everybody
crazy, and then there's the depression
side where everybody calms down, but
you're miserable, right? So, that's
bipolar 2. Bipolar one is when that
hypomomania goes into psychosis and you
have a complete break with reality and
you enter a space where you kind of feel
like you're dreaming, right? And back in
the 80s that usually is labeled anybody
back in the 80s who got acute psychosis
it would have been labeled
schizophrenia. But somehow along the way
the labels got shifted around and most
people going into acute psychosis today
get the label of bipolar one. So bipolar
one with psychosis, bipolar 2 just the
hypomomania and then both have the
depression on the other side.
>> Okay. And so that so that's the the
definition as broadly as the culture
knows, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. And then what I mean you you
seem to have discovered different
definitions or you you seem to have
expanded more on it. So I I guess what
would be kind of your definitions?
>> Yeah. So well there's it's not so much
uh that I disagree with that definition.
Like if if somebody has those symptoms,
I'm like, "Okay, this guy's in that
bipolar space." For sure. For sure. But
um what are the roots is the big
difference. And according to psychiatry,
the roots are biological. And like all
the DSM diagnoses, they they tend to say
that it's either genetic and then they
point to too much or too too little
dopamine or serotonin.
But the science shows that and this
comes from uh Robert Whitaker. He's a a
writer for the Boston Globe who has
taken on this mission. He has a website
maddename.com.
And what the science shows is that the
range of serotonin and dopamine are the
same for people with mental disorders as
they are for normal people. So there
while there is biological shifts
happening there is no inherent genetic
basis for a mental disorder you know um
and then actual mental illnesses that
take place usually involve memory loss
things like Alzheimer's dementia these
kind of things you you have problems in
remembering things okay uh mental
disorders don't take you or mental
illness doesn't take you into
non-ordinary states of consciousness per
Okay. All right. Like what you go into
in psychosis. Okay. So,
um my perception in talking to people
and and I have to go back to my own
experience for this, but what I believe
and and how I practice things is that uh
mental disorders, particularly bipolar
disorder, schizophrenia, because there's
a lot of gray area between those two and
depression have roots in trauma. And
that the trauma is somehow lodged in our
inherent bioenergetic system. Now in the
east they could call this system the
chakra system or maybe the condalini
system. Subtle body. Uh and condundalini
is like your life force energy. In China
they might call it chi or chiong. You
might have heard of chiong. The chi and
chiong. Um, so you've got this life
force coming through you and then
there's these blockages rooted in trauma
and when those blockages become too much
then that can cause a non-ordinary state
experience, you know,
>> um, like going into psychosis, you know,
but the roots of depression are the same
and that kind of thing. And then when
you go into these non-ordinary state
experiences,
uh there's only about 13 very spiritual
delusions that pop up and that's it.
There's like 13 of them. And then
there's uh if if a lot of fear comes
over you, there's also paranoia that can
creep in too. And hallucinations are
part of this as well sometimes with with
more severe situations. But for the most
part, we're talking about 13 delusions
that are obviously very spiritual.
Okay. So,
you said obviously very spiritual. One
thing I found um for my personal
experience was it took me a while to
even let words like spiritual into my
vocabulary. I didn't consider myself
someone spiritual. And so, like any any
of that stuff, I kind of just had a it's
not really for me. And it took me a
while to kind of actually start
comprehending those. Um, I'm at a
completely different place now. This is
many years ago. But, um, could you I'm
just thinking of someone who's
listening, maybe they've experienced
some sort of bipolar thing or they have
someone in their life, maybe they're in
that same boat that I was in years ago.
Could you maybe expand more on the word
spiritual? What might that mean to that
person?
>> Okay. Well, yeah, and according to Ken
Wilbur, there are 12 different uh
definitions for spiritual or
spirituality. So when one person speaks
about spiritual or spiritual things, it
can be interpreted completely
differently than somebody else, you
know. So there's a lot of confusion
around that topic. But um just to get
very practical and tangible when I'm
talking about spiritual delusions and I
and I made a video about this on
YouTube. My most popular video from
years ago was called Why You Think
You're Jesus.
>> People go into bipolar disorder and they
think that they are in psychosis. They
think they are either the reincarnation
of Jesus, giving birth to Jesus, they're
a messiah, they're Buddha, there's some
sort of figure here to save the world,
you know, and so that's like one of the
strongest delusions that that happen,
>> you know. It's like so it's like of the
sort of other worldly domain, you you
you might say, and what I see in that
case is people getting in touch with the
divine within themselves, you know. Now
conversely also spiritual and often
these days people don't think of it as
spiritual you can also have a demonic
side to this whole thing. Uh it tends to
be projected most of the time like it's
because it more fear oriented but you
can think often like the devil or demons
are after you. Uh, it can manifest as
aliens that are kind of evil, aliens
kind of following me around or
performing a surgery on me or something
like that. Um,
and uh, or you can even think that
you're the devil and and some people
think that they'll tell me that they
thought they were the Jes Jesus one
minute and the devil the next. And
because what's going on is
>> the energies are kind of flipping inside
of you. You're getting in touch with one
and then it turns and gets in touch with
the others. Because in this state, your
ego has broken down broken down and your
psyche is just running free reign
without control. You know, you've really
got no control in that situation.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It makes me think of um are
you familiar with Ramdas, the spiritual
teacher?
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. uh he he has this story where he
tells uh uh essentially he he had a
brother and his brother was uh actually
in like a psychiatric ward and he would
visit his brother and he would talk
about um his brother was was in that
same position he was he he thought he
was Jesus like he would just at all
times and it's funny Ramdas would talk
about you know here I am as this person
I've been in Nepal and India and I'm
wear I got a beard and I have these
malabads and I'm wearing like robes
essentially you know I look more like
Jesus than my brother does and He sainly
goes to visit his brother and uh him and
his brother get in some sort of quarrel
and the like the the final marker that
Ramdas puts on the conversation is uh he
tells his brother like the the problem
is that you think you're Jesus and I
know that we're all Jesus
>> and it's kind of this like it's not
necessarily about just the self like
there is some truth in what you're
feeling there is kind of this um uh with
spirituality you have to allow paradox
though it's not just this like you may
you may feel that you are having these
um
uh you know godlike uh experiences and
in downloads or whatever but it's not
that you are the one special person out
of 8 billion people who gets these it's
kind of like a human experience. So
anyway, um Ramdos mentions that and I
think that's a I always thought that was
a really good u teaching on that one,
>> right? And and it's a good indicator
also of how severe severe is a difficult
word, but how severe the disorder is by
how attached and how concrete the
interpretation is of what the person is
going through. So if you get somebody
back on medications for example and then
they're like I thought that I was some
sort of a Jesus figure you know speaking
of it in sort of
>> abstract or vague ways right
>> versus you don't understand I'm here to
save the world you know and and that
kind of person who who is just there I
am the only messiah that Jesus and you
need to respect me and bow down to me
wow that's a very difficult person to
heal, you know, or to help heal. But the
first one who was like, I'm pretty sure
I thought I was Jesus for a while, but
now I kind of get it and, you know,
they're taking a couple of medications
and that that that person you can help
if they've got insight into their
situation.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. Okay, Sean.
Well, um uh if if you'll give me I would
love to back up a little bit. So, I
heard a inkling earlier. I was listening
to you on the podcast and uh you were
talking about your one of your first
experiences into um kind of the
spiritual realm and and what kind of
started you down this path. You you were
at a landmark forum and and you had a
kind of a profound experience. Could you
break that down to me and could you also
just bring in anybody who's new what's
landmark? What were you doing there?
What were you trying to accomplish? Any
of that?
>> Sure. And and just to tell any of your
listeners, this story I tell in my first
book and it's available as a free PDF on
my website. Okay. Am I bipolar or waking
up is the is the PDF.
>> I'll have the link down below as well.
Oh,
>> okay. Great. So, what happened to me is
I was dealing with about seven years of
on again offagain depression. But it was
for me it was always around my career,
you know, just struggling with my
career. Uh but finally someone convinced
me to go take this course, the landmark
forum, landmark education. And at the
time I I didn't know anything about it,
but it was um rooted in something from
the 70s called EST training.
And it's just a very confrontational
weekend where they really kind of get in
your face about um who you are and what
you're about and how you're sabotaging
your life and and and really messing
with you psychologically. But because
there's 150 people in the room together
energetically it's really strong thing
too like I was going to the bathroom and
pardon my French farting like I have
never passed gas like this in my entire
life. Every break we had I had to go
into the bathroom and process internally
what the hell was going on. Like
>> for everyone
>> it was really uncomfortable and I've
never had an experience like that since.
Okay.
>> So funny. Yeah. But um and and they
controlled things like they told you you
you had to promise you will not go to
the bathroom while we're in session.
Like you won't just get up and walk out
the door. You needed to wait for breaks.
And if you couldn't agree to that, you
had to leave the course. Like they
wanted everybody on the same page, you
know. So it they created almost like a
cult-like environment where you just you
need to buy in or you're out the door,
you know. Um second day of that course
though they asked us to do a meditation
on our fear and I didn't think I felt
any fear. I was 30 years old at the
time. Didn't think I felt any fear and
then in the middle of this meditation I
saw a depth gauge from my scuba diving
equipment from uh Vancouver two months
earlier and I had I had had a scuba
diving accident. I lost my weight belt
about 90 ft below sea level. Okay. And
there was a moment there where I'm
looking at my depth gauge and I'm just
wondering if I'm going to die before I
hit the surface, you know, cuz I lost my
weight belt. I'm shooting up to the
surface from 90 ft below. I'm just
watching this thing and I'm exhaling
wondering if I'm going to make it to the
top, you know. Um, and I I couldn't
allow myself to feel any sense of panic
or fear in that moment because if you
did and you hold held your breath, that
could create an air embolism and you
could die. So, I was just very relaxed.
I just stayed relaxed until I hit the
surface, you know. But then on that fear
meditation,
I just had this huge punch in my chest
and just started balling. And then all
the fear came up and I could feel
everything and I was shaking and they
were encouraging us to go into deeper
fear imagery. I imagined myself sort of
being kidnapped and this kind of thing.
Um once that was over I my my senses had
completely shifted and I felt like I
could there was a sense of oneness
connection to everything lighter. I felt
like I knew things about life that I
didn't know before. Like before I always
felt like I was missing something. All
of a sudden it was okay. And then my
senses sharpened so I could see detail
in curtains I couldn't see before.
smelling things I couldn't smell before.
It was just everything was more vivid,
you know, and then I got really
emotional.
And this state carried on for about five
days and it takes about 80 pages of my
book. And then on the fifth day, I was
still on the course and I came to this
conclusion that I must have died in that
scuba diving accident because I felt so
completely different that this is what
heaven feels. Yeah. I was like I was in
the chorus thinking this is what it
feels like when you die and then all of
a sudden it was like oh that's what
happened. I'm dead.
>> Wow.
>> And I just thought everybody in the room
were actors that were just there to
uh play a role to help me move along in
my life and to move along to the next
level. And uh I eventually went into
this other room, this other ballroom cuz
it was all taking place in a ballroom
for this final night. And I just thought
I was going there to meet God. And part
of it was taking off all my clothes, you
know,
>> and uh also I peed on the carpet there.
It was all like a test. I had to let go
of everything. So I let go my bladder,
too.
>> And um eventually the police showed up
and I wouldn't put my clothes back on
cuz I thought this was part of the test.
And they grabbed me and put me in an
ambulance and took me to the hospital.
>> And I still thought I was going to
Nirvana or heaven or something. I was
trying to get to that other dimension. I
was sure I was dead. Um, but then a
couple of days after being in the
hospital, I started to realize nothing
was changing and that and my delusion
actually started to break down just by
the fact that I was still in the
hospital and people weren't particularly
nice to me.
>> And I thought, well, this is uh I don't
know what's going on, you know. Um, my
family was very supportive while I was
in the hospital. They were devastated,
but they were very supportive. When I
got home, I still had this feeling like
I'm having a spiritual experience. I
don't know what a mental disorder is. I
don't know what bipolar disorder is or
schizophrenia, but I had a spiritual
experience. And um and part of it is the
spiritual delusion, the common one,
feeling like you're dead, dying, or
being reborn, you know, that's one.
being feeling like you're being tested
by God is another very common one, you
know, and then another common one for
people is feeling like they're on a
special mission here to save the world.
But I didn't have that one because I was
dead, right? Like I I was moving on.
>> Um so all this happened in 1996, you
know, I want to make that clear to
people. And
>> it um after I had a few months to
integrate and I had a family friend who
was very understanding and and would
listen was a great listener. She was
from India. She had more of an open mind
than some of the others. And um once I
had that time I went back to work in
advertising which is what I used to do.
And my life got a lot better. My salary
tripled you know in 3 years. uh people
said they really appreciated me on their
business. They felt like I really cared
these kind of things, you know, even
while I w at that point I wanted to get
out of the business, you know, I was I I
needed to find some sort of spiritual
mission, you know. Um and after being in
advertising for a year, I met a I met a
Brazilian woman on a trip to Peru. I was
I had a dream I was being called to Peru
and I just kind of went on a tour. M
>> um there's a lot of details there, but I
I met her on a tour and um eventually we
got married and we moved to Brazil.
Okay. And so then then I became an
English teacher here and and my life got
much better. My years as an English
teacher were probably the best years of
my life. And that that took me sort of
between 2000 when I got married to 2007,
you know, and um but up up that whole
time I wasn't really involved in this
work. I I thought that spiritual
emergency and mental disorder were two
completely different things in that
period.
>> Right.
>> Right. Okay. So, going into this, what
was your
two questions, what was your background
and experience in kind of like a like
psychosis, bipolar, like were you
familiar with even that language? And
then also,
>> did you have how how about the language
of spirituality? Did were you spiritual
before? Did you grow up with any sort of
like Christian background, anything like
that or
>> Well, I I was raised Catholic and and I
had a strong interest in spirituality. I
studied religion in university.
>> I was actually trying to find the right
one, [laughter]
>> which didn't end too well. And I ended
up being kind of atheistic or agnostic.
Uh, and that had broken a few years
earlier, you know, with a with a trip to
Vancouver where I started to have like
synchronicities popping and things like
this. And it sort of opened me up to a
faith in something bigger than myself.
And and this happened two years before I
was in the hospital. So um one thing I
forgot to mention was that a year after
my hospitalization, I discovered the
work of a guy named Czech psychiatrist
named Stan Gra Stannislav Gr. and he had
written a book, The Stormy Search for
the Self, which talked about spiritual
um a kind of thing that looks like
psychosis but is actually spiritual in
nature and if you let it just play out,
it can be very healing.
>> And he called that a spiritual
emergency. And I had all the details on
a spiritual emergency. And and basically
to keep it really simple, he broke it
down to if you're able to internalize
what you're going through, it can be a
breakthrough. But if you externalize it,
it's a breakdown, you know. And but
[clears throat] he he he separated it
into two very different categories. But
for me coming out of that, I was like,
"Oh, I had a spiritual emergency. I did
not have a mental illness. And these are
two very separate things,
>> you know." And I I didn't even have any
interest in bipolar. I didn't know
anything about mental disorders. I
didn't think about them, you know, once
I was back to work, it was like, okay,
let me go live my life and find my true
calling,
>> you know.
>> So, did So, did you feel
did you I mean, this is a a hard word,
but normal. Did you feel normal
afterwards? Like, do like what was your
homeostasis after this episode? Like,
did you feel like a completely different
person still kind of or
>> I felt I didn't feel normal. I felt
natural. I felt a lot more natural. And
I was also a little weird. I I I think I
would be prone to sort of breaking
social convention more often than not.
Maybe I was always like that a little
bit, but then afterwards I was kind of a
little bit a little bit more. So I just
wasn't
playing by the typical rules, you might
say. But I had I kind of lost interest
in society to a certain degree. For the
years I was in Toronto after my
hospitalization on Saturday nights, for
example, I just stay home with my
parents. I had no interest in going out
and socializing that much. I felt like I
had this secret, you know, u because I
couldn't really share it with anybody at
work that I was just six months before
joining this ad agency, I was in the
psychiatric hospital. You couldn't
really
>> that to yourself. Yeah.
>> Yeah. You know, and and but then I got
interested in shamanism,
kind of a new age shamanism. And there
was a few events around Toronto. That's
where I'm originally from. And I would
go to a few events here and there. And
then I got um you know into this trip to
Peru and and that was just a fascinating
fascinating thing to do. Um, and my wife
and I like I met my wife in Peru,
Leisia, and we got married and we took a
in 2000 we took a big trip through her
country of Brazil, backpacked all over
the place and went and visited shamans
and um, pes they would call them all
over the Amazon and places like that and
just seeing in Salvador Bayya and seeing
you know the the descendants of slaves
in Salvador. or um channeling spirits,
you know, channeling African gods and
stuff like this. So, we I I was really
getting an incredible exposure to
>> the v variety of of experience you get
in Brazil
>> um both from religious and spiritual
perspectives, you know,
>> because it runs the whole gamut down
there and and and a lot of non-ordinary
state experience stuff happens with
drugs and without drugs, right? Um,
yeah. So, it was a fascinating place to
be when you were interested in
spirituality like I was at the time.
>> Yeah. And so, so it sounds like and you
hadn't written your first book by this
point, right?
>> No, no, no, not
2011. 2000 2001. Yeah.
>> And when did your book, when did your
first book come out?
>> 2011.
>> Okay.
>> So, it sounds like you were getting a
lot of info and new uh, you know,
stories and you're probably learning a
lot about this whole thing and about
yourself, right?
>> Yeah. And actually, I had written about
my hospitalization and given it to a
psychologist in the Toronto area just a
few years after it had happened to me,
but I never published it. I just kind of
kept it in the back burner. But then
once I got into this work about helping
people, then I published it as am I
bipolar or waking up in 2011.
>> And so, so how did you make that move
into like all right, I want to start
helping people. I feel that I have
enough knowledge about what happened to
not only me but now I can help other
people. How'd you take that step?
>> I was other than learning my own uh
learning about my own experience through
the work of Stan Grath and Ken Wilbur as
well. I wasn't I was just maybe looking
for a calling, but I didn't know how to
help people. I was involved in shamanism
in Brazil. Uh sometimes I'd work as like
a dog soldier, you know, which would be
like giving people water or something
like that. That's what they called it,
right? M
>> um
>> but uh in 2007, my wife's younger niece,
Anna, and that's important to point out
because it wasn't genetic. It was her
niece, it wasn't mine.
>> Um she went into an experience. We just
got a call out of nowhere and she went
into experience and her parents were
telling us what happened. And I was
like, "Well, that sounds like what
happened to me." And we went to support
her through it. And it was very close to
what I had been through. And I thought,
"Oh, well, this is a spiritual
emergency." And I talked to the parents
and tried to explain to the parents what
happened to me. I'd never told the
family what had happened to me. You
know, not that side of the family.
They're very conservative. But I thought
I need to get the fear out of that place
because the fear is what can really do
damage. So I really focused on that. And
my wife would support uh her niece. Uh
but and and we had good results. The
psychiatrist and psychologist both said
they had never seen someone recover so
quickly
>> than than she did. But they still gave
her the meds. And I was like, "Well, why
are they giving her the meds?" And and
then I they said, "Oh, it's gonna be a
few months of meds." And I was like, "A
few months?" And then then I got online
and learned it's going to be a lifetime
of medication. And that's where I just
went, "What the hell are we talking
about here?" You know, it was just
totally new news to me, you know. And
then I started to go deeper and I
started ordering books on Amazon and
discovered that actually there were
pioneering psychologists in the 70s that
went past the work of Stan Grath that
said that like they didn't deal with the
concept of spiritual emergency like he
did. They were saying that psychosis
itself uh acute psychosis is an intended
reorganization of the psyche. That's
what's really going on. And this and and
so if you could support that
reorganization without meds and just a
lot of patients, they can come through.
And there were places like uh a clinic
called Sataria House where they would
just practice being with people as
opposed to doing something to them. And
they were reporting an 85% recovery rate
with people in their first break. Okay.
And that was very important. So yeah,
they were sending people home just after
a week's stay of, you know, taking care
of them and being very supportive and
that was like a huge eye opener,
>> you know, that was a huge eye openener
>> and that got me really like oh well I
think I can do this, you know, I think I
can do this.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, so, so you found in that
situation you were able to bring, you
know, knowledge and wisdom and a
perspective to to your niece that nobody
else in that environment seemed to be
bringing like like did it seem that the
doctors that were, you know, they're
there to help her, but if they're not
trained in or they don't know any of
this stuff or they think it's all kind
of woo woo spiritual weird stuff that
has nothing to do with this, you know,
biology or, you know, the the chemical
imbalance, that whole that whole thing,
uh, that whole story that keeps getting
repeated.
Um, wow. Yeah. Yeah. How incredible. So,
how were people receptive to you when
you were bringing this stuff stuff up?
Were people letting you like explain
these things or did you feel you had to,
you know, keep your mouth closed in
doctor's offices or what?
>> It was a bit of a battle. And um, what
happened was after doing four months of
research into these pioneering
psychologists, I was going to go back to
the family and say, "Look, she let's
take her off the medications. if she
goes back into psychosis, we'll support
her through it. Like I'm learning about
you can do this with this sataria house
method of being versus doing. And just
as I was ready to go back to the family,
her sister came back from Europe and
went into psychosis.
>> Wow.
>> Like Yeah. It's unbelievable. Four
months apart, two sisters with no
psychiatric history went into
non-ordinary states. It's unbelievable.
Yeah. And she knew what happened to her
younger sister. So, I call them Anna,
the they're fake names, but Anna, the
younger sister, Elelliana, the older
sister. Aliana came to us first, and we
supported her. We didn't even tell her
parents we had her, and we supported her
um right through her first psychosis,
took her back to the family. She was
still ungrounded, but she wasn't kind of
crazy. Okay. And then she had a second
episode that we couldn't help her with
and she was medicated. But then she she
only agreed to go off stay on the meds
for two weeks. And when she went off the
meds, um she went into psychosis again.
And we had agreed with the family that
we would support her for that third
time. And and we did. And it didn't take
long. And then she was able to go back
to university medication free,
completely grounded. finished the year
with honors,
>> you know, went off to an amazing job and
and worked in 11 different countries.
>> Wow.
>> Um and um eventually did a master's
degree. Now, seven years in the future,
it would start to come up again. Okay.
So, it did start to come up again, but
we got her through. We got her through
university and she'd had those seven
years medication free. And because we
got her grounded and we knew we got her
grounded right away in the beginning,
then it was like, well, this is my life
mission. This is what I have to do. And
this thing,
>> this thing that I thought was a one in
20,000 kind of experience like what I
had all of a sudden I was realizing was
more like one in 20 because bipolar
disorder apparently affects 5% of
people. So I was like, "Wow, this is a
one in 20. This isn't a one in 20,000."
And that got me going, put it that way.
you know, and that's really the whole
story of the first book, you know,
spoiler alert.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Wow. No, no, it sounds
fascinating. And uh definitely again,
you have the PDF. We linked it below. Um
yeah, it sounds even just hearing about
your 80 pages worth in the landmark
form. I'm I'm curious to to to read more
about that. So, um wow, that's so
incredible. I mean, what what a you
know, I I think we could bridge this
into like the talk of synchronicities
and coincidences in in general. Um,
where do you because it sounds like in
this there's, you know, those are
synchronistic things. Those are
coincidences to me in some strange way.
Like how do you
where do you this is an impossible
question I know, but where where do you
kind of draw the edge? Where's the
sanity when it comes to synchronicity
and coincidences? Because you know when
I was in the impossible question, right?
But
I still these days I I feel very sane
and grounded in in my spirituality in in
these sorts of experiences. Um, but I
still have times where, you know,
there's a couple weeks, couple months
where I have these synchronistic
coincidental instances, but compared
them to my synchronistic coincidental
instances back, you know, when I was a
bit more ungrounded, they were very uh
if I tried to explain them to someone in
a logical manner, I just kind of sounded
off the wall. I could really would not
make any sense. Whereas now, I think I
could be able to explain those things
and they feel personal to me and I could
articulate them to someone else where,
you know, it's like, hey, this is part
of my spiritual experience. But anyway,
um, yeah. So, I guess where do we draw
the edge of of sanity in synchronicity
coincidences?
>> It's tricky. It's tricky. Uh, you know,
I told the family, I said, one of the
things I had to struggle with when I
came back from the hospital was
um, you know, am is this real or am I
dreaming? And they said, when did you
figure it out? And I said, I never did.
I just got used to it. And what I meant
was it's like we think we're in some
sort of a firm or fixed reality here
with logical reasoning and stuff like
that, but then every once in a while we
have kind of dreamlike material kick in
which is which is what you're talking
about psycho synchronicity. I mean when
that happens there are times when it's
actually impossible what just happened
you know um I tell a story in my second
book where I h I had a dream and it's a
long story but part of it is I had a
dream in like uh I think it was about
2016 August 2016
about seeing myself falling at a
distance I was watching myself falling
into a jungle canopy and I was wondering
if I had actually when I woke up I
wondered if I had entered it into a new
parallel universe of some kind like had
my reality really shifted in a way.
>> 8 months in the future,
so March of 2017,
I go with a client. We're in Mexico and
we go see King Kong Skull Island
together. It was like a little break
from our retreat work. And the opening
scene is the silhouette of a man falling
into a jungle canopy with the sun behind
him.
>> Wow.
>> So, I had seen the entrance to that
movie eight months earlier, and I was
telling the client's mother the story of
that dream just before we went into the
movie theater.
>> Whoa.
>> Yeah. And she popped up and said, "Shan,
your dream." And I said, "Yeah,
>> yeah,
>> yeah. I don't know what to do with
this." Yeah, what do I do with this?
This is just this is too much, you know.
So,
>> um I think life has a dreamlike quality
like that. And also, our dreams have a
kind of a reality quality like they
impact us more than we think we do.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean, you mentioned shamans, you
know, back in the day of shamans. It was
a very important I'm sure if we if they
projected in the future and they learned
that we kind of just ignore those eight
hours where we go to a different plane
of of reality every night. It's not
really a thing in our culture. It's
like, I had this crazy dream. It was
crazy. Anyway, what are you having for
breakfast this morning?
>> You know, it's it's but I think back in
the day, I think there was a you know,
sex of humans that used the dream world
maybe just as much as the regular world.
>> Yeah.
>> That the difference for them though,
what I've learned because I've studied a
lot of this stuff is they really looked
at the dream world as another reality
like this one, you know? So, for
example, if you if you dream that your
best friend is having sex with your
girlfriend,
it happened and you're going to go talk
to your friend about it, like, you know,
it's serious.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> But, but the level of importance is kind
of equal, you know, the interpretations
are different, but the for me, my dream
world is very important, and it's part
of the therapeutic work I do, you know.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. Um, okay. So,
I'm trying to think of so say the
listener right now um this is probably
all super interesting to someone who's
in this boat, but say that maybe they've
been diagnosed with bipolar um and and
they they feel okay. Maybe they're
they're medicated or maybe um maybe
they're not even diagnosed, maybe
they're experiencing some things right
now that uh might be up that alley or
somebody says they have bipolar, their
their sister has bipolar and so they
think it's genetic, etc., etc. Um and
they're listening to this stuff and
they're like, "What the heck? What does
this have to do with spirituality? Um I
guess like
>> well I I think in the bigger picture
>> um spiritual experiences like the one I
had or even things like psychedelic
experiences for example people often
report having spiritual experiences
while on taking LSD and things like that
or peak experience that can happen even
during sports um or different kinds of
rituals. they um
they give you a taste of this other
dimension but what you're doing with it
is is kind of the important thing and
and I think that uh the spiritual
dimension is just leading us towards an
authenticity you know like I said
earlier it's not about being normal it's
being natural you know and so uh when
people are healing which is the focus of
you know my work now it's about becoming
more open, spontaneous,
uh, and peaceful, you know, and present
th those kind of things. It's not about
being this Tony Robbins kind of super
god, you know, I was so productive last
week. I I slayed the world. It's like,
congratulations, Mr. Ego boost. I mean,
you know, it's not about that. It's
about it's about being really authentic
and honest with yourself. And and I
think to a certain extent healing is
about kind of cleaning out the lies,
cleaning out the we tell
ourselves. Not just about other people
or the lies we tell others, but the lies
we tell ourselves. Parts of us that are
just not being honest with ourselves.
>> I want to I want to expand into that
more so because that that resonates with
my experience. I had a lot of uh uh
things I was being dishonest with others
about and things I was being dishonest
with myself more importantly about. Um,
and I found that, yeah, that was a after
a while, you start when you're
dishonest,
you have these layers that you begin to
create almost accidentally of like these
lies that you have to keep up with. Um,
again, whether it's socially or just in
inwardly and then you kind of lose
yourself in between.
>> Um, is that is that something that you
would say is fairly common with with
people who have these experiences? Is
there some sort of external or internal
lie that maybe even they're not even
aware of? Maybe there's some childhood
thing that happened that they're not
really fully able to be truthful with in
the moment. Is is this common?
>> Right. Well, like the roots of the
disorder is trauma. Okay, that's a big
deal. And trauma in itself is kind of a
lie because it's taking a part of a an
experience that was so painful that we
deny the emotion itself. like, you know,
we just don't don't accept that that
happened. And and the best example, I
think, is when you see someone who's at
the funeral of a loved one and they
don't cry. And then they'll even ask
themselves later, they'll say, I don't
understand why I didn't cry. You know, I
loved him. You know, and people go to
therapy, why didn't I cry at my father's
funeral? You know, and the reason is
they're just so devastated that their
psyche has just checked it out and said,
"No, we're not going there." And then
and then it becomes locked into this bio
energetic system and can be a trauma
that leads to a deeper disorder.
>> And so how does our
um have you heard of or read the book
The Body Keeps the Score? You've heard
of that one?
>> I I I haven't read it. I should read it.
Really?
>> It's always brought up, right? Yeah.
It's always referenced.
>> Yeah, it's always brought up. I just
feel like I I it's like I know.
>> Yeah. You're going to be nodding your
head during the entire book, but Well,
but yeah, it's a huge book though. Very
influential.
>> Yeah. I mean, um I I think it always
just the book seems to be my doorway to
the conversation about kind of um um I I
think of like our fascia, our myofascial
system. I think it's kind of like a lot
of our spiritual like postures with with
the world. Um
>> Okay.
>> I
I kind of wonder so like how is how do
you see trauma being stored? Is it
stored in our physical body? Is it held?
Yeah, I see it in I see it sematically
like it's in our bioenergetic system.
You could call it a chakra system or
condundalini system. Um and incidentally
a year after my hospitalization I went
for roing which breaks up the fia tissue
>> you know and when you do that sometimes
that does release emotions and I did
have some of that happen in particular.
>> Okay. Um it yeah it's a very Have you
heard of raling? It's a very intense
It's a very intense massage where the
focus is on um kind of breaking up the
fia tissue which and the fa tissue is
like what connects your bones together I
think and once that's broken up you just
feel a lot more fluid and expansive but
it's been known that people will cry on
the massage table from having this
raling technique done to them you know
so for me the trauma is carried
throughout the body particularly along
the chakra line but it can be in other
other parts. And so that the key to
healing is to uh work on that the
therapy should be sematic. It should be
working with the body. And so in my
second book, I talk about the private
retreats that I set up. Took me a long
time to figure it out, but by 2013, I
started doing private retreats for
people.
And in those retreats, I was using a
technique from Stan Grath, a derivation
of the technique of holotropic breath
work. And with holotropic breath work,
you're over breathing in a very safe
space. You you're on a mat and yoga
pants and there's some powerful music
playing and you you're with a trained
facilitator, certified facilitator. You
do this over breathing and then when you
do that, the unconscious comes up and
part of it is very physical. So there's
a thing that happens called tatani where
your whole body can lock up your fists,
your neck, and some people get so locked
up they can barely even talk, right? And
they can go into panic. So it's good to
remind people that this can happen
beforehand and they can be locked up
there for like 30 minutes and then the
whole thing just relaxes and they feel
more relaxed than they've ever had for
their entire life. So this is just like
a wave of many traumas through their
whole body that is just being released.
you know, tension tension.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and so so so you've
you've experienced it through myofascial
release and then so in in your um in
your retreats that you set up, I know
you've talked a lot about a lot about
breath work and you you have developed
your own you kind of switched that into
you have your own bipolar breathing. Can
you tell me about that?
>> Yeah, that's right. Well, holotropic
breath work is a formatted thing because
there's a million ways to do breath
work. You know, you can do breathing
that's just like relaxation meditation.
You can do things that are supposed to
activate your condalini processes, you
know, pranayyamas and things like that.
But with holotropic breath work, um
you've got uh a safe space, trained
facilitator, like I said, powerful
music. It's a three-hour session
generally in a group. Okay? It can be
private, but also in a group. And that's
the format. And that was contraindicated
for people with deeper disorders because
they were afraid that that it might open
up too much and the group setting or the
limited time frame would be a wouldn't
be a safe enough container for someone
who's dealing with more difficult issues
like you might have if you've got
bipolar or schizophrenia. So I said to
myself, well, I'm not doing anything
right now. How about if I start my own
retreat? And that way I give people
unlimited time frame and unlimited
attention, just private attention. And
and I insist that they bring a
volunteer, a volunteer supporter, so
that I'm I'm not on my own. I I can get
breaks while they can still be
supervised. The family knows somebody's
with them, so they know I'm not just
some weirdo from the internet. Somebody
from the family is sort of involved. Um,
yeah. And then with the bipolar breath
work, I just made a few adjustments
which is they can start and stop
whenever they want, you know. So if they
just decide after 20 minutes that's it,
I say okay, that's it and we stop and
then we come back to it when they want.
That's the first thing. And then there's
the undivided attention and I can also
customize the music depending on where
they're at. So they were the three of
the big adjustments I made early on, you
know, um, and the results were
incredible.
>> Yeah. What so what are the kind of
experiences people that you saw people
having?
>> Yeah. Well to to point out like the
sematic aspect of this whole thing you
know which is uh condundalini and the
blocked energy. My first client had been
hospitalized I think about 10 times and
um every year for about a month for six
years and when I went to work with her
she had a pain in her coxix that was so
bad she couldn't sit down for more than
10 minutes and she couldn't lay on her
back in bed. Right.
And in the fifth breath work session we
did, she didn't move a muscle, very
quiet. I thought nothing was happening.
And then she came back and she told me
hot energy came shooting out of her
coxix up the spine into the shoulder
blades down through the hands. And the
pain that she had been to six medical
doctors for and they had no answer for
her. The pain was gone.
>> You know, after five sessions, we knew
right away and synchronistically we we
knew it was part of the disorder. or I
had suspected it. She had told me about
the coxix pain even before I went there.
And uh when that cleared up, when that
cleared up, I thought she had been
healed. Okay. I thought,
>> I'm a genius. This is done.
>> Here's my bill. You know, I'm now
>> Yeah. I'm Jesus. Right. I'm Jesus. Uh
but she did have an episode a couple of
months later
and I got on the phone with her. I said,
"I'm coming back to Romania. I live in
Brazil. come back to Romania and you
don't need to pay for anything. And we
did a second retreat
>> the second year 2014
and then she was medsree for five years.
It was meds free for five years after
that. So again it was like she come in
2016 I met her again. I was in Romania
three years in a row um
synchronistically and she came back she
visited me and she said Sean I've been
off my meds for a year. That hasn't
happened since I was 20 years old. you
know, like for 15 years, you know, and
she was able to remain off her meds for
five years, you know.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you know, that she was my first
client and and then after that,
>> my next two clients in Germany and
Finland had incredible success and and
they're both completely out of the
psychiatric system. They no medications,
no relapses for over a decade now.
>> Yeah. That that's incredible. Okay. So
bring me bring in someone who I think
you you and I it's not that shocking um
to hear you know there's this physical
pain in someone's body. It's at it's at
this area where we know it's like okay
this is like maybe stuck energy in your
root chakra. That'd be language that you
and I would probably know. But someone
else would be like wait okay so you're
saying this lady went in to six
different doctors. She had pain that
couldn't get solved. It was not on an
X-ray anywhere and she breathed and it
helped with you know.
>> Yeah. Yeah. and then try to tell a
psychiatrist that, you know, the roots
of her mental illness are spiritual and
in her ass.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> It's like, okay, I I give up. I can't do
that, right?
>> Yeah. [laughter] Yeah. But clearly,
you've had success with this. So, so how
do you how do you break this down to
people? How do you how do you explain
this in a way that that people can wrap
their heads around?
>> I made a lot of YouTube videos.
>> Sure. made a lot of YouTube videos and I
and I and I made um
>> well and the books help. But what I
learned on YouTube is that even though
I'm talking about information that it's
pretty complex, you can take the ideas,
as long as you break them down into
small pieces and give people things that
they can relate to. Like one of my most
popular videos that people still watch
was like one about the spiritual
delusions and I called it I think I
called it uh uh is it bipolar disorder
or spiritual enlightenment
>> and then I talk about the delusions that
look like enlightenment and I think I
say so whether you're a Buddhist monk
going through this in a cave in in Tibet
or you're a teenager in Chicago who just
took some LSD your experiences look
pretty much the same. Mhm.
>> You know, there's not. And funny enough,
intensive meditation,
going on a 10-day retreat is a very
common trigger for acute psychosis that
gets people labeled bipolar and then
they're medicated for life, you know.
So, it's not just, oh, these kids are
taking drugs and and now they've ruined
their lives and they're on these meds.
It's very common drug use, but on the
other end, intensive medication and
meditation can bring the same thing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. you well you had a didn't
you have a 10day vaposa experience
didn't you have a spiritual experience
on it
>> yeah I had one in
>> I had one in 20 2009
and energetically it felt stronger than
what put me in the psychiatric hospital
>> Oh wow
>> um and it left like again explosion at
the heart chakra all my organs shaking
vibrating
crying but more tears of joy
>> but I was so shook up and this is during
the meditation that I was afraid to walk
back to my room cuz there was a hillside
trail and I thought that if I fainted I
might fall down the the hill and never
be se seen again. You know [laughter]
this kind of thing. So and I was
basically in bed every morning for the
next five days. Um and it was stronger
in a condalini sense than what put me in
the hospital. But I at by that point I
knew what I was doing. I had been around
the work. It had been my mission for
three years. So when this condundalini
process unfolded
>> then it was like I was bit bit more
ready for the whole thing you know
>> and then and then the heart of the
condalini stuff continued for the next
six months. I'd be in bed with my wife
and then you know good night. Oh like oh
what's that? H just hot pins in my toes.
Thank you.
>> Yeah. [laughter] Yeah. Ju just a Korea
honey. Don't worry.
>> Yeah. Is that what they are? Kas.
>> Oh, the ka is the prayer, right?
>> Well, so ka, my understanding is ka is
the involuntary movement. Um, it is the
like the sudden like the you know,
you're trying you're in meditation and
you can't really help but you know
anybody who's going through a kunalini
experience, especially if you're doing a
lot of yoga too, you can't really help
but like do all that kind of stuff.
That's my understanding of Korea. I
could be a little bit wrong on that, but
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. No. And uh and I still
work with Kundalini processes to this
day. Um I go through a lot of jerking.
>> Um but um but for the first six months
it was quite uncomfortable.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, so where where
do you where would you say that you sit
with it now? um after you know after
this many years of of it as your
personal experience where
um you know like like when someone comes
in and they would like to know kind of
your your background of not only your
experience with with condundalini and
your spirituality and everything what is
kind of your explanation to them like
hey I had this experience happen here's
how I see it now um cuz because to me
you come across as very grounded with
this sort of thing and so I kind of
wonder um how you observe yourself or
how how you see others seeing you when
you explain it.
>> Well, I don't talk about it that much
for regular people. I I'm the kind of
person like I look for the open door or
I look for people who seem to be looking
for this kind of help
>> and then if they come to me like like a
say you guy like you, you know, you're
very open, you're very receptive and
you're curious and you want to know,
right?
>> But I don't stand on the street corner
trying to tell everybody about what
happened to me. Um and when people say
oh how do I convince my family to
understand that what I went through is
spiritual I tell them I say don't just
uh look for someone who's open or if
someone comes to you and you put a few
feelers out there and they're open and
curious talk about it but if not just
just keep it to yourself because people
get threatened by this kind of thing and
and and if if you feel like they're not
listening in the beginning they're not
you're not going to change their mind.
You're not going to change their mind.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I agree. Um I
where I've come at wi w with my
experience with it is um yeah I'm in
that same boat like I don't I don't go
advertising it. Um, sometimes it's like
I I I'll go many months without even
talking about it with friends or
whatever and it's like it's crazy this
like very profound, you know, to me very
important experience happened to me that
changed the course of my life, but it's
like I haven't even really thought about
it much, whatever. But I'll I'll note
that uh it will come up in cool
conversations where it feels natural, it
feels safe, it feels that I can be
useful to the person that I'm talking
to. I actually had one time on a plane.
Um, I'm I'm mostly an an introvert in in
public on planes. You know, I'm kind of
just like to, you know, have have my
hood up, have headphones on, just kind
of keep to myself. I don't typically
dive into a bunch of deep conversations
on planes, but uh I had one probably
year and a half, two years ago
>> where um I started talking to this to
this girl next to me. She was super
super cool, super polite. Um and over
the course of the time, it was like a
5-h hour flight. I ended up learning
that her sister
>> had been going through um basically
psychosis and she was like going through
all these things and
>> I I allowed this girl to tell me quite a
bit before I even was like well here's
kind of my thoughts if you're willing to
hear you know and I kind of tried to
explain without you know this girl had
never heard you know these terms
condundalini or you know she doesn't use
terms like chakra I think she had like
more of a a Christian background so you
know some of those terms in itself are
sometimes s people can think they're
demonic for some reason. Um
>> but but anyway, so I ended up great
connection. I I gave her a lot of these
resources. I was like, "Hey, check out
this channel. Check out this person.
This could be all totally, you know,
just my perception. Uh you know, but
maybe send your sister these. See what
she thinks. Maybe have a conversation
with her. Maybe you could talk to your
mother about these things, you know,
just to open up the conversation with
your sister." And she seemed to be very
very grateful. And I was like, you know,
that that was cool that I was able to
this stuff that I'm obsessed with, this
stuff that I like learning about that
happened to me, I'm able to kind of
casually open up and potentially maybe I
I helped out that person's sister in
some way of giving her some resources.
So yeah, like I wasn't going about
looking for like who wants to hear about
my condolini awakening on this plane,
you know, but uh but it just happens.
Yeah. And I I will add though that uh o
over the last 18 years of doing this
work, you know, starting in 2007, now
it's 2024 and I was making videos and
I'm writing books and I'm doing
retreats, there was often a tremendous
sense of mission and that I hadn't
finished my mission, you know, and and
sometimes it would just bring me to
tears, the frustration about just not
getting where I needed to go, you know.
But then when I finished the second book
here and uh you know bipolar awakenings
the quest to heal bipolar disorder at
the end of the book I was just like I've
done my part. It's like if the world
just wants to just forget about me at
this point, I've done everything I'm
supposed to do.
>> And um and I I there's a sense of relief
to a certain degree. And then I created
an online course and then the relief got
deeper. And so now it's like, well, I'm
not really sure what I'm supposed to do,
but I like to talk about it. So I I've
started to do more podcasts and
>> the curiosity is kind of over. I'm not
in the research and development part of
the work. I'm I feel like I want to be
just talking about the work instead of
doing it at this point. Like being a
teacher instead of a therapist, you
know?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, I think it's a good
spot to be, man. I I more and more
people w with the internet especially,
you know, YouTube is such a cool thing,
especially with,
>> you know, we live in this. It's not
necessarily a social media algorithm.
It's like a a interest algorithm at this
point, you know. So, somebody starts
watching,
>> you know, they watch this one. We talk
about Kundalini a lot. And you know now
their algorithm is going to feed them
more more kundalini type stuff which I I
do I do think
>> this could be another interesting part
of our conversation Sean is um
>> do you think that uh like philosophizing
and reading about this content can cause
a condundalini awakening? Do you think
contempor
psychosis for people just watching my
videos has caused like condundalini
awakening? You want to call it a
condolinia awakening? you want to call
it psychosis. I my website like my book
it's called bipolar awakenings. So I
kind of put in that the paradox that
this thing can cut both ways you know it
can be a blessing it could get leave you
medicated for life depending on how you
deal with it.
>> Yeah. You know, so any information about
this, reading a book, reading a
spiritual text is a common what I call a
trigger.
>> You know, common triggers are like death
in the family, going to university is a
common trigger because you're changing
is the most common trigger because
you're changing cities. You're leaving
your family behind. You're being exposed
to people you've never been exposed to.
People from different parts of the
country, for example. You're typically
not doing as well at university as you
did in as you did in college. Like
you're probably the top of the class in
high school. Then you're just one of the
dregs when you get to university. Can be
very challenged in the ego and you might
be doing a lot of drugs too. So you put
all that together, it's a recipe for
psychosis, you know.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Or bipolar awakening. It's a recipe for
bipolar awakening. We'll put it that
way.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Either way, your yourself
will be challenged. Um, okay. So, so
where do you see the self? Where do you
see identity? Um, do do you think as a
culture we should be reshaping the way
that we um interpret and talk about
identity and ourselves in these things?
>> Uh, wow, that's a deep question. I don't
know if we're ready for that depth.
What's your identity? That's that's kind
of tricky. But, um, you see, I think
we're starting to veer there a little
bit. you you you hear people talk, oh,
there's one place where it really comes
up a lot. There's all of these fake
videos on YouTube by um they say they're
the words of Carl Young and they're the
words of Alan Watts, you know, but once
you get past the fact that well, it's
not really Carl Young and it's not
really Alan Watts and they're both dead
and
>> so like how is Alan Watts talking about
social media? He died in 1973. There was
no social media, you know. Once you get
past that though and you and you listen
to how they talk about life and living
and um this thing that's even I'm just
learning about still a process of
individuation,
>> you know, where you're pulling your
projections back from the world, you
know, you're you're pulling back
codependent relationships where you're
looking for other people to fulfill you,
you know, um which is a typical
marriage, you know, that's a a
codependent relationship is a typical
marriage. But when you look at that,
it's like, okay, it's natural, but maybe
it's not optimal. Maybe there's another
way to sort of come at it, you know, and
I I was divorced last year and we had a
very good marriage, I think, but and
we're still friends, but there was a
part of it where I realized, whoa, hang
on. Like, I've sacrificed a lot of
myself by being in this marriage there.
There's a real codependency going on
here, and I got to figure that out, you
know?
>> Yeah. So, and and this year has been a
lot of deep introspection and often very
painful
um and a lot of somatic movement and um
jerking through the chest, the belly,
the hips, the neck clicking. Anytime I
would just sort of settle down and focus
on my own emotions, it would be like my
body would take on a life of its own.
>> Yeah. It's almost like you got to um
like physically embody who you're now
supposed to become or something like
you're, you know, like physically
[clears throat] changing into who you
are next or or something, you know?
>> And the weird and synchronistic part
would be like I'd put on one of these
like Allan Watts or or or um Carl Young
videos on YouTube and listen to them
>> and I I noticed that sometimes my body
would spontaneously jerk on specific
points,
>> you know? Yeah. and be like, "This is
what you're looking for, jerk." You
know, and it was like, "What is doing
that? What is causing my body to
spontaneously convulse on specific words
in this video?"
>> Yeah.
>> You know, it's a it's a divine and I
should bring it up too and and you see
it in the breath work is the healing
agent is actually a divine intelligence.
It's a higher power. You can call it
God. Could be aliens. It could be an uh
could be um angels, but it's definitely
a higher intelligence. And working with
people on 10day retreats, you see how it
unfolds and it's pretty amazing.
>> Yeah. So, so how do you when you come
across someone with a a more atheistic
background who who like I said before,
you know, doesn't necessarily love all
these spiritual words, doesn't really
have a place in their, you know, psyche
or understanding of who they are for
kind of um, you know, this this divine
being much larger than, you know, my my
uh lowercase me self. Uh, how do you how
do you navigate that with him? like are
they able to if you're able to describe
like nature or the laws of nature does
that help with them to to kind of
penetrate that or
>> No, it doesn't help. Um and this is
where the work of Ken Wilbur really
comes in and Ken Wilbur talks about the
evolution of consciousness. All right.
>> Yeah.
>> And one of the things he says is that
the the first stages of consciousness
like the first six stages and we have
four that are very common. The first two
are very infantile generally are related
to to illness and then the next four are
pretty common and they're all trying to
get the other people to see the world
the way they think and and the biggest
the strongest example is when a
religious person who is constantly
trying to convert other people to their
religion you know but at the same time
the the diversity crowd the LGBTQ crowd
they they do the same thing I mean if
you don't see the world through their
lens. The MAGA crowd, if you don't see
the world through their lens, it's like,
you know, you're I don't know, you need
to be deported
either. Yeah. You're evil.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so they will see
different stages of consciousness will
see the other person as evil or stupid
um or yeah, like a sinner or just
something's very wrong with them, you
know. But at a certain like once you
realize the developments going on, your
intention is to help people out. And so
if somebody is say say for example, you
got a a former drug addict who goes to
church every Sunday and that's what's
holding his life together.
Beautiful. That's where he's supposed to
be. Is he a racist? Sure he's a racist.
Let him be a racist. He's got bigger
issues than his racism because he's
gonna die if he does if he leaves this
church, you know. Um, but then other
people are struggling with certain
stages like maybe maybe you're getting
more rational and and you're wondering,
well, is Jesus even real? you know, if
you're having these kind of thoughts or
um then you can introduce to them ideas
that are a little more atheistic because
that will be an actual step forward, you
know, to to get people thinking
rationally is a step forward. But then
what happens when people are atheistic
is eventually they lose meaning in life.
Like what's the point of living? You
know, it existential angst is a very
common depression for people with
atheism or yeah, like it's a disease or
something. And I was one of those
people. I just when I was athe or
agnostic, which is like where you ra
scientifically believe that it's
impossible to prove that God does or
doesn't exist.
>> I felt like I was in a lost world, man.
I was just
>> I didn't know what to do with my life in
my 20s. All the depression, you know.
But then coming out of that atheism, if
somebody is really in that existential
angst, like if they're proud to be an
atheist and they're successful and
they're doing well and they're
materialistic, good, let him go. Let him
do his thing. But if he's struggling,
then you could say, well,
what's your intuition telling you?
>> You know, do you want to stay in your
job? Do you want to live in this city?
Do you want to stay in this
relationship? And if the answers are no,
it's like, well, well, then what is your
deeper intuition saying? And once we tap
into the intuition,
>> then we're starting to follow like the
inner voice of God, you know, like this
the divine intelligence within or or in
a bigger picture even if you want to go
way out there, the quantum field like
the quantum intelligence,
>> you know, because I'm a parallel
universe guy at this point, you know.
So, I think there's a whole bunch of
Shawn's, you know, there's one Shawn
that's a drug addict and one Shawn's a
priest and there's another Shawn that's
a doctor somewhere and and then I don't
know what the hell I'm doing here, but
it's it's pretty trippy, I can tell you
that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Another Romas
thing. He he has this thing he always
repeats like I I'm in this one over
here. How'd you get into that one over
there? [laughter] And he always says
that. It's always really funny.
>> Something like that. Something like
that. Yeah.
>> Yeah. But um yeah, I like that though,
you know, trying to find a way in their
language that doesn't um you know, close
them off, you know, because I find that,
you know, a lot of people shut down with
a lot of these a lot of these words, you
know, a lot of these therapy speak and
spiritual language and all of this stuff
nowadays is um
>> it's not only a lot, but it's very uh
like like you said before, triggering,
you know, like just a few sentences can
really make someone lock up and then you
know, you're not going to really get any
progress with them.
>> Yeah. And everybody's everybody's on
their own journey and to a certain
degree, as much as you want to help
somebody and I want to help a lot of
people, but that journey does need to be
respected.
>> Mhm.
>> To the point where I'm just kind of I
think I'm more kind of nonchalant about
what I'm doing now more than any other
time.
>> Uh and in September, believe me, I
wasn't. But I think I had some sort of a
breakthrough of of of a sort
>> after an extremely painful September.
And then now it's more just like, "Oh,
good. Let's go to the beach, you know,
and just accept what's coming."
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, happy November to you,
sir.
>> Thank you. Yeah. It's been a better
month. Been a better month.
>> Paradoxically, drinking a lot of beer
lately, funny enough. It's like I' I've
been Mr. No Drinks, but I'm living in a
town where there's just a lot of drunks
in this town.
>> Yeah.
>> And I meet my friends on the weekend and
we have some drinks and I do it more to
be social than anything else. But yeah,
>> you know, you know, I I I thought about
two things lately. Both alcohol, the uh
the liquid courage as they call it, as
well as small talk. You know, I went
through periods where I was very against
both. And uh I thought it was so much
cooler than small talk. And then um
yeah, I've really been thinking a lot
lately, these last few months of how
great small talk really is to just we're
we're just kind of looking for a
connection. It's not so easy to just
dive layers deep with a stranger right
away, and you don't always want that.
it's okay to like how do I find a way to
just smile with another individual and
sometimes it's laughing about the silly
traffic or the weather, you know, and
and um in that same realm, as much as
like alcohol has, you know, it's a a
spirit and uh you know, it has all these
negative things. if you deal with any
sort of like depression or bipolar,
maybe alcohol isn't always your friend.
But, uh, it's also
>> you know, half a beer in and I'm
remembering how much I love this friend
that I'm getting to have a conversation
with and just talking about whatever
without it needing to be all spiritual
and deep and we're, you know, laughing
about fart jokes or whatever it is.
You're connecting, right? You know,
those simple things that at some point
in your path you push away,
>> they come back around.
>> Yeah. And and I think that's a little
bit synchronistic in my own process
because that you're saying this because
I'm a person who does not like small
talk like really but now I'm living in a
city by myself. I've got a few close f
well I got a few friends here and I'm
learning
that superficial conversation is just
the way it's going to be and you might
as well enjoy it, you know.
>> Yeah. And so I am more active about the
small talk. How's the weather? You know,
this kind of thing. What are you doing
this weekend?
>> Well, you kind of find, man, that
this this is kind of like a little bit
corny, right? But you kind of find that
you could still find a way to love love
someone without like your favorite
language, you know? Like I can go to a
if I'm on a road trip and I'm in
Louisiana and I stop at a gas station
and I I can tell maybe the person's
having a rough day or or whatever. Maybe
I don't even analyze their life at all
and I just have a quick little
two-minute conversation and it's kind of
silly about whatever they were talking
about. It has nothing they didn't learn
about my deep knowledge of philosophy or
they didn't learn about my uh whatever
thing that I think is going to bring me
joy or happiness. But I walked away and
I'm chipper as I'm walking out of that
store and I they're smiling whatever.
You know that's
>> I don't know that's that's connection.
You know
>> it's to tell you the truth. I think the
best thing like cuz I live alone and
sometimes I can get a little lonely
sometimes. I think the best thing I can
do for my own loneliness when it comes
up is just get in an Uber. Book an Uber
for like 20 minutes. You know, I have
great conversations with Uber drivers.
Yeah.
>> You know, they got nothing to do. Well,
they're driving around all day and and
I've had some really fun funny
conversations with Uber drivers both
here in Brazil and in Canada.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I had a guy thank me the
other day actually for for talking to
him because he was a little bit little
bit of a language barrier and I could
tell he probably gets a little
frustrated trying to but um you know we
were talking. It was a little clunky but
at the end he was like, "Thank you very
much for for taking the time to talk to
me." I'm like, "Dude, of course." Like I
can't believe you just had to thank me
for talking to you, you know. [laughter]
I remember I I had an absolute nightmare
of a retreat in India in South India.
Can't go into the details. It's in the
book. But they threw me out. They got
spooked by what I was doing basically.
>> Oh wow.
>> And they put me in this taxi for a
4-hour taxi ride back to the airport.
And at one point I just go, "Raj,
yes, sir.
Do I seem like a bad person to you? He
goes, "No, sir. You're a cool guy, sir."
[laughter]
>> Yeah, man. [clears throat] It was like
Raj was my therapist in that moment, you
know. Sorry for the Indian accent. I had
to do it.
>> No, I love it. I'm I'm so glad you did.
I'm I'm a huge fan of uh comedy. I'm
actually going to a comedy show tonight,
so I'm I'm great.
>> And anywhere I could insert comedy into
the conversation, I'm in, man. So, thank
you for it.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um, okay. Well, uh, I I want to I
would love to talk a little bit more
about Kundalini itself if you don't
mind. So, um,
>> go for it.
>> I'm always, like I said since the
beginning, I'm always kind of trying to
bring along the person who's new, maybe
they're in the car ride or they're, you
know, they're with their significant
other who likes my podcast and they
don't really know. I'd like to like
bring people aboard so they can feel
like they're part of the conversation.
Um, you know, you know as well as I do
that kundalini is a it instantly feels
very far-fetched. It's like there's a an
energetic snake coming out of my butt.
What are you talking about? um you know
but uh bring it back to kind of like
this divine energy that is you know
within all humans and it could be you
know activated release like like I I
think the best way to describe it seems
cheap to those people when I say it I
feel but uh I would say like you know
Jesus had an awakened condundalini you
know I would say the Buddha had an
awakened condalini I don't know these
for a fact but I think it's just a good
way of explaining like
>> they yeah
>> they were you know
>> again not that us having kundalini
awakenings means that were like now
enlightened as just regular people or
something. But um I don't know. How do
you demystify the word kundalini, Mr.
Black? Well,
>> how do I de demystify it?
Well, I I like to start by saying that
there was in like about the 1930s, there
was a guy named Gopi Krishna in India
[clears throat]
and he had dedicated his life to God and
meditating every day and then all of a
sudden it started with him and one of
his symptoms was uh he just had this
insatiable thirst and no matter how much
he drank his mouth was always hot. He
was always burning. That was one of his
symptoms of his condalini process. Okay.
My first client, Livia, she was dealing
with the same thing. She called me a few
months after one of our retreats. Sean,
I'm just drinking water all the time. I
can't get rid of this burning mouth. You
know,
Gopi Krishna at the time, he knew he was
in some sort of a condalini process and
he knew that it looked very similar to
madness.
He contacted every guru he could get in
touch with, every mystic guru in India
that he was aware of, and there were a
lot. He couldn't find a single one that
had had a condolini experience.
>> Wow.
>> Okay, we're talking about Indian mystics
in 1935.
These experiences are very common now
for completely untrained people. Okay?
Regular teenagers having condundalini
experiences. They don't know what's
going on, but sometimes they just follow
their intuition and spontaneously start
to move with this stuff to sort of
unlock it, you know, and other people
become afraid of it, you know. So, what
to make of it? I think that we are in a
bigger kind of a global awakening of
some kind. Uh, Grath was big on the
astrology of the whole thing. And I
think that and and this gets woo woo.
Okay, this does get woo woo, but I think
that there's a just a need for
authenticity that's happening now in our
world that earlier generations never
thought to go to even with their most
intimate partners, you know, like you
and I are having, I think, an incredible
conversation, you know, which I have not
had with Oh, I could probably count on,
you know, my finger my fingers how many
times I've had a conversation where I
felt someone is so just with me and
real, you know,
>> because for the most part
that authentic connection, I think
you're better off trying to find that
with your cat than with, you know, a
family member or something like that. So
there's something there there's a demand
for authenticity.
And one of the things that's coming up,
I'm sort of meandering around the
question, but
>> please do. You're great. Yeah. where
where we met on Pod Match.
There's all kinds of Pod Match profiles
of of a bunch of different podcasts and
the one word that keeps coming up in
everybody's podcast profile right now is
the word raw. Everybody is saying, "Oh,
this is the place for raw conversation."
Raw. Raw. Raw. Unfiltered. Unfiltered.
Raw. Unfiltered. Raw. Unfiltered. and
almost to the point where it's kind of a
joke.
>> But
>> people I think maybe it's because of the
AI coming in are getting brittle against
inauthenticity. They want real life
experience. They want real connection.
And to have that, you do need to get
more honest with yourself, you know. Um
and therapy can help, but I don't know.
Oh, I think there's a lot online that
that can help these days as well. And
and and it's a it's an introspective
movement. And once you start to get
introspective,
the condolini is just going to pop, you
know, eventually. It's going to it's
going to show up in in different ways
and and you're going to realize it
eventually, I think.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Wouldn't that be wild if all
the podcasters just start having
condundalini awakenings? [laughter]
Well, and it's a different kind of
conversation you have as a podcaster,
too, because
>> you guys are having and and I've done
some podcasts, too, but it's like, okay,
here we are, 60 minutes, just me and you
uninterrupted,
you know?
>> Yeah. How often do you do that?
>> Not too often.
>> Yeah.
>> Not too often. Yeah. Yeah. About things
you're genuinely interested in, you
know? So, it's a it's a very different
kind of thing. I I'd feel more connected
to you, for example, than I would uh my
uh neighbor that I see every day, that I
see physically every day.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, I've never had a conversation
like this with him, you know.
>> We talk about the women at the beach. We
talk about drunks. We talk about some
gossip about the neighbors and and
that's our thing, right?
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Like what's around us right here,
you know?
>> Yeah.
>> You don't get too ethereal or too meta
or too, you know, bird's eye systems
thinking.
>> No. and we I have fun with this guy.
He's a great guy, you know.
>> Of course.
>> Yeah. But it's not it's not like this.
This is a whole other This is a kind of
a conversation that I think can inspire
people.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I think so, too. I mean,
you know, that that's why I I like to do
them. Um you know, obviously I love them
too, but you know, I I like to think
that there's I keep referencing like the
listener. You know, when I first started
um the me starting this podcast years
back was kind of at uh not like the
height of it, kind of on like the
decline of of my kind of awakening. And
uh I was I had been listening. I was
>> I started basically I wanted to solve
all my childhood trauma. I wanted to fix
everything that was broken about me, you
know, and so I just went to town with
excavators and shovels and everything
about my psyche and my insides and I
really just tore it up and I was really
um you know pretty loosey goosey for a
little while and uh I was listening to
podcasts and I was just learning so much
and I listen to audiobooks and I'm
taking notes and I'm just unraveling
learning so much and it was so fun and
so great and so awesome. I was just I
felt like a new person every day. I'm
just shedding layers, right? And uh I
would hear things on a podcast like some
you know a couple dorky comedians
talking about whatever in two hours and
13 minutes in this one guest would say
this one sentence that would just like I
have to pause it and I have to like sit
down and it just changed me and it I'm
just I've never heard anybody talk like
that especially like a man in this
instance whatever. And so I would notice
[snorts] how just casually listening to
podcasts would profoundly change me, you
know, and so that led in that was a lot
of the reason why I started doing the
podcast and and things too. So, you
know, I'm sure I'm not the only person
in that boat, you know, and so isn't
that cool to think that we're all
changing one another by sharing our our
personal conversations and other people
could listen in on them.
>> Yeah. I've never thought about that
before, but certainly people listening
to authentic raw conversation
>> Yeah. is going to have implications for
real life, you know, because people will
start to be more authentic in their
daily lives with their friends and
things like that. They're going to want
to open up. They're going to want to
reveal themselves more. And it's it's
self-revelation. And as you peel back
those layers, then all of a sudden you
get the tweaks and the burning and the
the heart palpitations and the leg
twitches and all that kind of goofy
stuff. The pins in the toes and yeah,
>> all those condalini symptoms,
>> all all the fun exciting stuff. Okay.
Well, um I I want to be respectful of
your time, Sean. We are uh getting
towards the end here. Um so, say someone
is interested in this. They love all
that you've said. Um you know, they're
going to go check out your websites and
and and everything. What's what's not
only new on the horizon for you? Bipolar
Awakenings is your most recent book
there. Um firstly, would you this is
probably a hard question to ask an
author. Would you recommend your first
one or your or your second book if you
had to choose one as like their first
intro to your work?
Oh, good question. If you don't know me,
then um the first one, it's an easy
read. It's a two-day read, right?
>> Nice.
>> Yeah. The second book after every
chapter, you need to sit down.
>> Yeah.
>> You you just need to be like,
>> did this really happen? Oh my god. And
you just need to go and digest and take
a break. And and it's and it's
annoyingly deep and detailed. Um and I
love it. It's for my money, it's better
than the Bible, but that's just my own
unbiased opinion, you know.
>> Sign me up. Sounds good, man. Sounds
awesome. [clears throat]
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Well, cool. Okay. So, so they'll check
out your your newest book or maybe dive
into your older older teachings.
>> Both are free PDFs on my website,
bipolar awakenings.com. Oh,
>> they're both free PDFs. That's amazing.
That's cool that you offer that.
>> Yeah. And I and I've got some online
therapeutic approaches that I use, too.
We haven't had time to get into it, but
you know, that's something we bring up.
I also do a free 30-inut consultation
for people.
>> Can I I don't want to I don't want to
rush past it. We do have a few minutes.
What uh can you tell me a little bit
more about your online online courses?
What what do you offer? What can they
get into?
>> Well, on my retreats, I learned that I
was picking up the unconscious materials
of my client like their pain.
>> Oh, that's I actually had notes about
this. I did want to ask about this. So,
yes.
>> Okay. Well, I and so to make a real long
story short, with the help of uh one of
my clients who became a supporter,
Monica Kettler, I always have to give
her credit, too. We realized that we
were picking up unconscious material
from the clients. And that having us
breathe on behalf of the client,
actually going into the client's pain
really strengthen the retreat process.
Yeah.
>> Because for example, I've got tons of
experience in breath work and it's not
my pain. So if I'm breathing on your
behalf, I can go into things that you're
not ready for. You know, [clears throat]
>> that became standard part of our retreat
process. First my client would breathe
and then I would breathe after that.
Then I learned, guess what? This works
at a distance. I can do distance work
like this. And that's a long story I I
get into in the book, but um so I have a
thing called distance surrogate breath
work that I can do on people's behalf.
And basically, it's a two-hour session
where I'm listening to breath work music
and twitching and twerking, you know,
working out whatever I feel is going on.
And then the client will have some sort
of synchronistic material so that they
know that I'm working on them. Most of
the time it's dreams that come
afterwards where they know it's their
material, you know, they just know that
this is about their life. Like
>> last week I had a dream about having to
apologize for my criminally oriented
brother and this guy had a d had a
brother who had been to jail. You know I
that kind of thing. Um it could also be
visual things that pop up during the
session although that's less common
these days and sometimes physical
sensations and and sometimes
simultaneous physical sensations. So, I
was in a session with a guy from New
York, and at about the 20 minute mark,
my arms just snapped right out of their
sides, and when I finished the session,
I got a text from him. Man, my arms just
snapped right out of my sides.
>> Whoa.
>> Yeah. Like, crazy stuff happens where
it's like, you know, you're connected,
you know? So, and if you don't, I I'm
open to return people's fees. So, that's
something that I do for people. And I
also have a training program where I'm
if people have a supporter, I'm open to
teach the right people how to do breath
work in their own home if they've got
someone who's willing to learn the
training with them.
>> So far, I've had no takers,
>> but that's there, too.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I I guess we'll see.
>> Yeah. I keep trying to make the work
cheaper and more accessible, but keeping
it safe as well, you know.
>> Sure. Yeah. Yeah. Um, okay. So, I I I'm
sorry I keep having more questions come,
but how do you and Monica
>> How did you how do you I don't want to
say protect yourself because that sounds
like um how do you not only stay sane
and protect yourself, I guess, but um
how do you
like once you notice, okay, this is not
only this this is not my energy to work
with now, let me transmute it. But
first, how do you even get to the point
where you can decipher your intuitive
like the things you're working on versus
other people's energy? How do you
>> uh Well, the first thing is that that
while it's with me, it feels like it's
my own, you know, and so I just treat it
like it's my own and go through it as if
it's my own material. But then once I
look at the content and I look at how I
see feel later, it's pretty clear that
it's the client's material. Because when
it's your material and you work through
it, like this is your own unconscious
material surfacing. When that happens,
it leaves a lasting impression with you
and sometimes you need to sleep on
things. You need to think about it. For
example, if you had some anger come up,
you might feel angry after the session,
for example, that kind of thing. But
when it's somebody else's material, it
just passes through you like energy.
Even if it's angry or shameful or or
birth related and you just look at it,
you go, it's like you're watching the
whole thing happening. It's moving
through you
>> and and you don't have any ego in the
game. That's another part of it. It's
being done by the quantum field. This
the inner healer is actually a healing
field that is sending that energy to you
to process. Right?
>> So you're just acting like a servant or
something. You're just you're you're
just cleaning whatever is coming your
way. That's it. So um if you think, "Oh,
I'm the big guru and I'm going to heal
you." That's not going to happen because
there's too much ego in the picture.
need to genuinely want to do this for
people and uh want their best best needs
at heart, you know, and you just filter
it through like it's your own stuff.
>> Yeah. I I love that.
>> Pretty easy, actually.
>> Yeah. I I was I love that I was able to
ask that because I I had a lot of
struggles. Uh I think, you know,
probably a lot of people who go through
this stuff are would consider themselves
somewhat of empathic, you know, in some
ways sensitive at the very least. Um,
and and I I went through a lot of
struggles of absorbing other people's
energy. And it was very confusing to me
for a while. And it took me a while to
kind of like feel when I'm grounded in
my own body and feel when, you know, I'd
be at times where I could have like just
walking by someone, I would suddenly be
like distressed and whatever. And
instead of launching off into my solving
intellectual mind of like why is my life
this like this and what am I doing and
blah blah blah just kind of allow it and
then within a few seconds it's like
passes through and I go, oh, I don't
even have to solve that. that wasn't
mine to solve. I just just passed
through, which is so strange, right? But
I think it's a useful thing to learn how
to do.
>> Sure. And Yeah. And things have happened
to me on the street like just by
accident walking by somebody and then
all of a sudden I have a feeling for a
situation and all of a sudden, whoa,
whoa. Like Yeah. I've kind of got to be
open and compassionate, but it's
generally quite spontaneous, you know?
It's not like I'm walking around, you
know, in white robes or anything like
[laughter] that. It's just
>> give me your bad vibes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You know, congratulations,
you've got bipolar disorder, you know.
>> Yeah.
>> No, it's it's just happens. I just deal
with it and um and that's it, you know.
It's it's and and it's common. I there
have been supporters who've come on my
retreats. They just really care about
the person. You know, we had a we had a
girl on one retreat, 23 years old, no
experience with my kind of psychology,
and then she was falling asleep during
her boyfriend's session at 10:00 in the
morning. Normally, when I'm absorbing
energy from a client, I'm getting really
drowsy. Really, it's like it's a magnet
that sucks you in, right? It was
happening to her. So, I said to her, "Do
you want to breathe?" Afterwards, the
session was over. She says, "Yeah." She
starts to go into her boyfriend's birth
process. Next thing you know, she's like
I have to simulate a uterus for her and
she's got her head going through my arms
and then like I'm I'm hanging on to her
and she's struggling out of my grip and
I've got to hang on down through the
hips and the legs and the feet like
she's being born. And then I said to
her, I said, "Did you have any sense
that that was something related to your
life?" And she was like, "No, that was
fun." [laughter]
What?
>> She just
>> What a trip.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and it was her
boyfriend's birth material.
I mean, talk about codependency.
>> Yeah. She had no training at all. None.
You know, so I was like, "Wow, if she
can do this surrogate work, then anybody
can do it for anybody if they've got the
empathy." And she did. She had the
empathy.
>> Yeah. I mean, wow. How incredible is
that? I mean, and I think like you
already stated, I think a lot of us have
discovered since especially since 2020,
how we are able to do those sorts of
things virtually, too. you know, we're
able to not only through video Zoom
calls, but like you said, if if you and
the other person are both aware that,
hey, this is what we're going through at
the same moment together, it really
does. I mean, wow, what a we have so
much to learn about the the capacity and
capability of of the the human mind and
how it integrates with physical reality,
right? [laughter]
I I had a call once with a girl where I
was explaining how the psychic material
comes and I said suppose for example I'm
working with you and I see a red violin
and then that might be something related
to your life and then actually I said
actually did do you play violin and
she's like yeah I play violin I grew up
playing the violin this is my favorite
instrument I was like okay that makes
sense okay you know these kind of things
>> so Yeah.
>> Yeah. They're like little um uh little
crumbs from from the from our greater
selves or crumbs from the universe or
something, you know, synchronicities. I
I don't know. I I I love that humans are
always discovering more about ourselves.
As we, you know, heal ourselves, we're
really learning and remembering who we
really are. You know, it's as we're as
we're learning more, we're almost
unlearning and and remembering who who
we already are.
>> Seems that way. Seems that way. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Still mysterious. still frustrating, you
know. I still don't know how I'm going
to pay my bills this month. But
>> you and me both, brother.
>> It's been quite a ride, though. So,
>> yeah.
>> Yeah. We're all just walking each other
home, eh?
>> I hope so. [laughter]
>> We're going somewhere.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Uh, all right, Mr. Sean Blackwell. Well,
well, um, I would love to just give you
one more opportunity. if there's
anything that is at the the the the edge
of your mind or something that we didn't
mention that you kind of wanted to bring
up um any uh you know bows to tie
anything like that. I just wanted to
give you that opportunity or anything
that you would like to leave the guests
with.
>> No man, I think it's been a terrific
conversation. I think we've pretty much
said all that needs to be said on this.
Obviously, you and I could go back and
forth for another 10 or 20 or 200 hours.
I think
>> easily 100%.
>> Yeah. But uh yeah, if anyone's
interested in my work, you can access
everything at bipolar awakenings.com.
Both books are free PDFs there. There's
a link to my YouTube channel, you know,
the whole bit.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Um listeners, you'll
you'll check out those links below if
you want to check out some more. Sean,
you'll have everything you need um down
below. And uh man, if you uh if you
write more or you work on some more
projects in in the past and you'd like
to have another conversation, I would
love to have you anytime, Sean. So,
please just reach out anytime, buddy.
>> Wow, that's great. And if I'm in Austin,
I'll definitely look you up.
>> Yeah, that would be excellent. That
would be excellent. All right, man.
Well, hey, uh, I'm wishing you the best.
Thank you again so much for your time. I
hope you have a good rest of your day.
Listeners, you know the drill. What I
always say at the end of every episode,
drink some water, stretch, love
yourself, slow down, and uh, subscribe.
We'll see you next episode.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Knowledge is power.
[music]
Reality is
>> [music]
>> Junkyard Love